

🛘 (+61) 410 988 821 | 🗷 alexander.soen@gmail.com | 🏕 https://alexandersoen.github.io/ | 🖸 alexandersoen | 🎏 Alexander Soen

Summary.

I am interested in a wide range of research topics. Previously I have worked on topics including formal methods / theorem provers, visualisation in academic influence, knowledge graphs, and universal approximation theorems. I am also interested in point process models. My primary focus is on utilising boosting algorithms, information geometric tools, and the theory of loss functions with a focus on fairness and privacy in machine learning.

Education

Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science

Anticipated Graduation 2024 July 2021 – Pres.

The Australian National University; Canberra, Australia

GPA: 7.0/7.0

THE AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY; CANBERRA, AUSTRALIA

Bachelor of Advanced Computing (R&D) (First Class Honours, University Medal)

2016 – 2019

Secondary School

ATAR: 98.75

RADFORD COLLEGE; CANBERRA, AUSTRALIA

2014 – 2015

Publications

Published / Accepted († with minor revisions)

[1]	Rizoiu MA, Soen A , Li S, Calderon P, Dong L, Menon AK, Xie L, "Interval-censored Hawkes processes"	† Accepted in JMLR
[2]	Soen A, Sun K, "On the Variance of the Fisher Information for Deep Learning"	NeurIPS 2021
[3]	Soen A , Mathews A, Grixti-Cheng D, Xie L, "UNIPoint: Universally Approximating Point Processes Intensities"	AAAI 2021
[4]	Shin M, Soen A , Readshaw BT, Blackburn SM, Whitelaw M, Xie L, "Influence flowers of academic entities"	IEEE VAST 2019

Preprints

riepinits			
[5]	Soen A, Alabdulmohsin I, Koyejo S, Mansour Y, Moorosi N, Nock R, Sun K, Xie L, "Fair Wrapping for Black-box	2201.12947	
	Predictions"		
[6]	Soen A, Husain H, Nock R, "Data Preprocessing to Mitigate Bias with Boosted Fair Mollifiers"	2012.00188	
[7]	Calderon P, Soen A , Rizoiu MA, "Linking Across Data Granularity: Fitting Multivariate Hawkes Processes to Partially	2111.02062	
	Interval-Censored Data"		

Research Experience

PhD Student Canberra, Australia

Australian National University

2021 – Pres

- · In collaboration with the interdisciplinary Humanising Machine Intelligence group at the Australian National University.
- Developing novel algorithms using tools from theoretical machine learning and information geometry, with applications in algorithmic fairness.
- Produced publications [2,5,6].

Interval-Censored Point Processes – Research Assistant

Sydney, Australia

University of Technology Sydney

2020

- Worked in a Facebook funded project which involves the collaboration of computer scientists and social scientists to study hate speech.
- Built and deployed various web-crawlers from scratch in Python using numerous APIs.
- Developed new algorithms to fit interval-censored data to Hawkes Process; which resulted in publications [1,7].

Knowledge Graphs - Research Assistant

Canberra, Australia

Australian National University

2020

- Collaborated with departments of the Australian Government to integrate different data sources for analysis.
- Created a software pipeline to create knowledge graphs using various technologies (RDF, SPARQL, external APIs).

Point Processes and Neural Networks - Summer Research + Research Student

Canberra, Australia

Australian National University + Australian Signals Directorate

2018 - 2019

- · Collaborated with the Australian Signals Directorate in linking different types of Hawkes process models.
- · Proposed a novel architecture for incorporating universal approximation of neural networks for Hawkes process models.
- The work resulted in publication [3].

Visualisation of Academic Influence - Research Assistant

Canberra, Australia

AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY 2017 – 2019

- Maintained and developed the InfluenceMap website (influencemap.ml): a visualisation tool for examining citation and publication based influence patterns in research.
- Worked with Microsoft Academic API to gather the data used for visualisation.
- · Presented and demoed the project at the 2018 ACM Multimedia Conference business meeting in Seoul, South Korea.
- The insights and tools developed resulted in publication [4].

Theorem Provers - Summer Research

Canberra, Australia

AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY

201

- Investigated translating formal semantics defined in HOL4 to executable code in CakeML.
- Presented a talk with a poster at the Fifth Data61 Software Systems Summer School.

Other Experience _

Teaching AssistantCanberra, Australia

AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY (VARIOUS COURSES)

2017, 2020 - Pres.

- Taught courses ranging in topics from machine learning, data management, to logic (various conveners).
- Previously helped design and release course material, including, original assignments and lecture plans.
- Taking a head tutor role in 2022 for a machine learning course of 250+ students, which includes overseeing course design and day-to-day logistics. I have advised in the material and topics taught in the course; and have been strongly involved in developing and creating all course content including examination material.

AngelHack Sydney

Developer – TeleNex 2016

- Developed TeleNex, a web application to assist mental health professionals that tracks a patient's emotions in real time.
- Won the UN Women's Code 4 Impact Prize at the Hackathon.

Honors & Awards

0	Australian Government Research Training Program	2021
0	Australian National University: University Medal [Top 2 First Class Honours Graduates]	2019
0	Ian Ross Honours Scholarship [High-performing Honours Student] (\$5000)	2019
0	Honours Scholarship with the Australian Signal Directorate (\$8000)	2019
0	Summer Scholarship with the Australian National University (\$5000) $ imes 3$	2016 - 2018

Coding Proficiency

Programming Python (Adv.), R (Inter.), C (Inter.), Julia (Basic), Coq (Basic), ML (Basic), Haskell (Basic), Java (Basic), Javascript (Basic)

Machine Learning PyTorch (Adv.), scikit-learn (Adv.), Tensorflow (Inter.)

Other Bash (Adv.), LaTeX (Adv.), Git (Inter.)

Other Contributions_

Reviewer for Top Computer Science Conferences

• Reviewed various papers for a variety of top conferences, including, ICML [2022, 2021]; ICLR [2022]; NeurIPS [2021]; WWW [2021].

Computer Science Student Association (Australian National University)

COMMITTEE MEMBER 2017

- Was a General Representative for the society, making decisions and planning events for students.
- Proposed and ran various events, including, study events for official course exams and installation events at the start of the academic semester.